<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--

    dsh-venn-cytoscape-plugin  Cytoscape plugin for venn and euler diagrams.
    Copyright (c) 2010-2012 held jointly by the individual authors.

    This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
    under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as published
    by the Free Software Foundation; either version 3 of the License, or (at
    your option) any later version.

    This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT
    ANY WARRANTY; with out even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU Lesser General Public
    License for more details.

    You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public License
    along with this library;  if not, write to the Free Software Foundation,
    Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307  USA.

    > http://www.fsf.org/licensing/licenses/lgpl.html
    > http://www.opensource.org/licenses/lgpl-license.php

-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>venn-cytoscape-plugin</title>
  </properties>
<body>

<section name="Summary">

<p>
dishevelled.org <b>venn-cytoscape-plugin</b> provides Venn and Euler diagrams for
Cytoscape [<a href="#1">1</a>] as a plugin.  The Venn and Euler diagram Cytoscape plugin
requires java version 1.6 or later and Cytoscape version 2.7.0 or later.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Venn and Euler Diagrams">
<p>
The plugin provides a diagram view and a details view for comparing two or more
Cytoscape groups at a time.
</p>

<p>
The diagram view is an interactive Venn or Euler diagram showing the number of nodes
in each logical grouping.  Clicking on any area in the diagram selects the corresponding
nodes in the current Cytoscape network view.  The diagram can be exported to an
image file in PNG and SVG formats.
</p>

<p>
The Venn diagram view uses a symmetrical layout that supports two to four Cytoscape groups.
Venn diagram views for two and three Cytoscape groups use two and three circles respectively.
For four Cytoscape groups, a symmetrical construction of four ellipses is used.
</p>

<!-- 2n, 3n, 4n venn diagrams -->

<p>
The Euler diagram view uses an area-proportional layout that supports two or more
Cytoscape groups.  A Euler diagram is similar to a Venn diagram but does
not display all possible intersections.  The Euler layout allows an exact area-proportional
Venn or Euler diagram to be generated when the data allow it and a statistically-justified
approximation of a Venn or Euler diagram when the data do not [<a href="#2">2</a>,
<a href="#3">3</a>].
</p>

<!-- 2n, 3n, 4n euler diagrams -->

<p>
The details view shows the nodes in each logical grouping.  The selection model
of the details view synchronizes the selection for all of the list views (i.e.
selecting a node in any one list will select it in all lists) and exports the
selection to the current Cytoscape network view (selecting a node in the details view
will select it in the current Cytoscape network view, but not vice versa).  The
details view supports two to four Cytoscape groups.
</p>

<p>
Screenshot showing the venn diagram and detail views for comparing two groups:
</p>
<p>
<a href="images/binary.jpg"><img src="images/binary-thumb.jpg" width="500" height="364" alt="Screenshot of binary diagram and details"/></a>
</p>

<p>
Screenshot showing the venn diagram and detail views for comparing three groups:
</p>
<p>
<a href="images/ternary.jpg"><img src="images/ternary-thumb.jpg" width="500" height="366" alt="Screenshot of ternary diagram and details"/></a>
</p>

<p>
Screenshot showing the venn diagram and detail views for comparing four groups:
</p>
<p>
<a href="images/quaternary.jpg"><img src="images/quaternary-thumb.jpg" width="500" height="312" alt="Screenshot of quaternary diagram and details"/></a>
</p>
</section>

<p>
Screencast demonstrating the venn diagram views and interactions with the group plugin:
</p>

<iframe width="640" height="510" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UtoW0nVwOV4" frameborder="0"></iframe>

<section name="Availability">

<p>
The Venn and Euler diagram Cytoscape plugin is available for download via the SourceForge project download page<br/>

&gt; <a href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/dishevelled/files/venn-cytoscape-plugin">https://sourceforge.net/projects/dishevelled/files/venn-cytoscape-plugin</a>
</p>

<p>
or via the <a href="http://apps.cytoscape.org/">Cytoscape App Store</a> at<br/>

&gt; <a href="http://apps.cytoscape.org/apps/venndiagrams">http://apps.cytoscape.org/apps/venndiagrams</a>
</p>

</section>

<section name="References">
<p id="1">
[1] Cytoscape<br/>
&gt; <a href="http://cytoscape.org">http://cytoscape.org</a>
</p>
<p id="2">
[2] VennDiagramGenerator<br/>
&gt; <a href="http://apps.cytoscape.org/apps/venndiagramgenerator">http://apps.cytoscape.org/apps/venndiagramgenerator</a>
</p>
<p id="3">
[3] Leland Wilkinson, "Exact and Approximate Area-Proportional Circular Venn and Euler Diagrams," IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, pp. 321-331, February, 2012<br/>
&gt; <a href="http://www.computer.org/portal/web/csdl/doi/10.1109/TVCG.2011.56">http://www.computer.org/portal/web/csdl/doi/10.1109/TVCG.2011.56</a>
</p>
</section>

<section name="Acknowledgements">
  <ul>
    <li>Powered by Apache <a href="http://maven.apache.org">Maven</a>.</li>
    <li>Project hosting by <a href="http://sourceforge.net">SourceForge.net</a>.</li>
  </ul>
  <p><img src="http://sourceforge.net/sflogo.php?group_id=113165&amp;type=1" width="88" height="31" border="0" alt="SourceForge.net Logo"/></p>
</section>
</body>
</document>
